Finding Aid for Harold K. Jacobson (1929-2001)Papers, 1957-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harold K. Jacobson papers 1957-2001, 1980-1999
Jacobson, Harold Karan (1929-2001)
3.5 linear feet
042 Aa 2
Harold Karan Jacobson, professor of political science at the University of Michigan, was primarily involved in the areas of international relations, peace and security, behavior of states, foreign policy, and global environmental change. These papers represent his work as a professor, researcher, and author.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor 9199 ) were received in May 2002
The collection is open without restriction.
Harold Karan Jacobson was born in Detroit, Michigan on June 28, 1929. In 1950 he received an A.B. degree "with distinction" from the University of Michigan. He received an M.A. and a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1952 and 1955, respectively. After research and teaching positions at Yale and the University of Houston, Jacobson joined the University of Michigan as an assistant professor of political science. He was a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Sciences. He also served as the director of the Center for Political Studies at the University of Michigan Institute for Social Research (ISR), and was acting director of ISR from 1992-1995. He served as interim associate vice president for international affairs at Michigan from 1990 to 1992, president of the International Studies Association, and vice president of the International Political Science Association.
Jacobson was an expert on international institutions and politics, including international relations, law and organizations; foreign policy behavior of states; peace and security; and global environmental change. His research focused on the implementation of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change and on democratic accountability and the use of force by international institutions. He played a leading role in the creation of the International Human Dimensions of Global Change Program, and was a member of the National Academy of Sciences National Research Council's Committee on the Human Dimensions of Global Change. Jacobson was the lead author of the 1994-1996 second scientific assessment of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.
Jacobson authored, edited, or co-edited 12 books and numerous articles and monographs on international institutions and politics. His last book Engaging Countries: Strengthening Compliance with International Environmental Accords, was co-edited with Edith Brown Weiss of the Georgetown University Law Center, and is based upon National Implementation research.
Jacobson received numerous awards during his career, including an award for International Scientific Cooperation from the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1995. He also received the University of Michigan Press Award, the University of Michigan Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award, the Amoco Good Teaching Award, and the Excellence in Education Award. Harold Jacobson died at age 72, on August 13, 2001.
The Harold K. Jacobson papers are divided into seven series: Topical Files, National Implementation Project, Lectures, Papers Presented, Human Dimensions of Global and Environmental Change, University Materials, and Published Materials. Types of information and materials include research notes, correspondence, and lecture notes primarily related to Jacobson's work as a professor of political science and his interest and research into nations' adherence to international environmental laws and international politics.
Subjects:
Jacobson, Harold Karan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; Environmental protection--International cooperation.; Environmental law, International.; Political science--Study and teaching.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (0.8 linear feet, 1965-1996) consists of papers related to some of the committees, organizations, and projects that Jacobson was associated with. The files within this series are arranged alphabetically, and relate to fraternities, international initiative projects, conferences on international issues, international environmental policy, and committees within the University of Michigan.
  - Alumni Association Continuing Education Program 1979 (Box 1)
  - Area Centers
    - Reports 1992 (Box 1)
    - UCIAA Correspondence 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Retreat 1992 (Box 1)
  - Capital Campaign 1990 (Box 1)
  - Center for International Business
    - Business Education 1990 (Box 1)
    - Hong Kong Training Program 1995 (Box 1)
  - China in Time and Space 1994 (Box 1)
  - China Data Center 1995 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Teaching Ethics and Values in the University 1986 (Box 1)
  - "Diplomats, Scientists, and Politicians," 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia of Life Support Systems 1996 (Box 1)
  - Ford Library Conference 1982 (Box 1)
  - Gerald Ford Library Colloquium April 11, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Honor Societies
    - Sigma Iota Rho 1986-1993 (Box 1)
    - Phi Sigma Alpha 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Indiana University Conference on Local and Global Common Problems October 1993 (Box 1)
  - International Initiative
    - Vision Statement 1990 (Box 1)
    - Ford Symposium on Becoming more International and Global 1992 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation Request and Organization of Symposium 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Technology Access Project UM/MIT/HARVARD 1990 (Box 1)
  - Inter-Center Council 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - International Center June 29, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Internationalization Meeting, Paris 1992 (Box 1)
  - IGO Paper 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Korean Studies
    - General 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - Fundraising Activities 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Conference April 10, 1992 (Box 1)
  - London Trip 1991 (Box 1)
  - Language Statement 1992 (Box 1)
  - National Identity, Human Rights, and World Order Symposium 1992 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Multi Lateral Trade Negotiations Project 1987 (Box 1)
  - President's Weekend
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
  - South Africa Trip 1991 (Box 1)
  - Student Survey 1993 (Box 1)
  - United Nations University Project 1995 (Box 1)
  - Wall Street Journal (Asia) 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- National Implementation Project
  The National Implementation Project series (1.5 linear feet, 1991-1996) consists of materials related to Jacobson's work on this research project with Edith Brown Weiss of Georgetown to study nations' adherence to international environmental treaties. It contains such files as correspondence with country participants, grant applications and budgets for the project, background research into different nations' adherence to international environmental treaties, and working materials for the book that Jacobson co-edited with Weiss, titled Engaging Countries: Strengthening Compliance with International Environmental Accords.
  - General 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Short Project Description (Box 1)
  - SSRC Proposal "International Laws and Global Environmental Change," 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - MacArthur Application 1992 (Box 1)
  - NSF Application 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - NSF Advisory Panel 1992
  - Country Teams 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Agenda 1993 (Box 2)
  - Bellagio Conference Proposal "Improving Compliance with International Environmental Accords," 1993 (Box 2)
  - Young Scholars Listing (Box 2)
  - Narrative Report to the MacArthur Foundation 1993 (Box 2)
  - Narrative Report to the Ford Foundation 1993 (Box 2)
  - Budget 1993-1996 (Box 2)
  - Comprehensive Project Codebook (Box 2)
  - Addendum 1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - with Wu Zijin 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - with Social Science Research Center 1992-1996 (Box 2)
  - National Implementation Seminar in Geneva June 1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meetings
    - Barcelona 1994 (Box 2)
    - Washington D.C. January 1994 (Box 2)
    - Hawaii February 1994 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor December 1994 (Box 2)
  - World Trip May 1995
    - Switzerland (Box 2)
    - France (Box 2)
    - United Kingdom (Box 2)
    - Japan (Box 2)
  - SEER Meeting Report 1994 (Box 2)
  - Netherlands Workshop "Implementation of Environmental Treaties," 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Supplemental Travel Grant 1994 (Box 2)
  - Reports to NSF 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Treaty Compliance Dataset, Codebook, and Worksheets (Box 2)
  - Environmental Treaties 1991 (Box 2)
  - Japan Codebooks 1993 (Box 2)
  - London Convention of 1972 (Box 2)
  - Montreal Protocols (Box 2)
  - World Heritage Convention 1993 (Box 2)
  - Compliance with International Environmental Accords 1994 (Box 2)
  - Convention on International Trade in endangered species (CITES) (Box 2)
  - UN Framework Convention on Climate Change (Box 2)
  - Book, "Engaging Countries: Strengthening Compliance with International Environmental Accords"
    - General 1993 (Box 2)
    - Abstracts (Box 2)
    - China (Box 2)
    - Chapter 2 (Box 3)
    - Five International Environmental Agreements (Box 3)
    - Charts Mailed to Authors of Political Unit Studies (Box 3)
    - Returned Charts (Box 3)
    - Charts of Treaty Variables (Box 3)
  - Reports and Charts (Box 3)
  - Presentations 1994 (Box 3)
- Lectures
  The Lectures series (0.2 linear feet, 1963-1996) is arranged chronologically and contains notes and outlines from the various public lectures that Jacobson gave around the country and overseas. Each lecture is in its own file, and covers topics such as international relations, decision making in international organizations, and international policy. Classroom lectures are located within the University Materials series.
  - Chicago Alumni Talk, "Test Ban Treaty," 1963 (Box 3)
  - Wilton Park, "Decision Making in International Organizations," February 1971 (Box 3)
  - Scientific Club, "The UN: How Dangerous a Place?" 1979 (Box 3)
  - Camp Michigania, "Perspectives of SALT," 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Conflicts and Alignments in Contemporary World Politics," 197? (Box 3)
  - "The Christian and World Government in the 1980s" February 1980 (Box 3)
  - "Can Nuclear War be Prevented?," 1980, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Scientific Club, "Nuclear Weapons and Arms Control," 1982 (Box 3)
  - "The UN and Political Conflict," May 1983 (Box 3)
  - Toledo Lecture October 1983 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Tenure Workshops 1983 (Box 3)
  - "Hegemony and World Order," Beijing June 1983 (Box 3)
  - "The Crisis in Arms Control," 1983, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Conference on Japanese and American Response to an Unknown Future June 1984 (Box 3)
  - "The Crisis of the Liberal Prescription for World Order," New Haven, Connecticut 1985 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Model UN February 1985 (Box 3)
  - Oakland University November 1985 (Box 3)
  - Bowling Green State University April 1985 (Box 3)
  - "The U.S. and the UN," Mount Union College January 1987 (Box 3)
  - "Preparing for a Global Future: What are the Choices?" University of Michigan 1989 (Box 3)
  - International Law September 1993 (Box 3)
  - CIESIN Librarians Meeting 1994 (Box 3)
  - UN Fifty, Ann Arbor, Michigan October 1994 (Box 3)
  - Village Club 1994 (Box 3)
  - Conference on the Holocaust March 1995 (Box 3)
  - Law School Seminar 1995 (Box 3)
  - Scientific Club April, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Conference on Infusing International Dimensions into Political and Social Science Curricula, 199? (Box 3)
- Papers Presented
  The Papers Presented series (0.2 linear feet, 1961-1987) is arranged chronologically and consists of different papers that Jacobson presented around the world on topics related to international relations, policy, and politics. This series also contains Jacobson's congressional hearing statement on U.S. policies in the United Nations.
  - "Freedom, USSR, and ILO," 1961 (Box 3)
  - Canadian American Relations 1962, 1963 (Box 3)
  - "Civilian Operations in the Congo," 1964 (Box 3)
  - "The International Telecommunication Union," 1969 (Box 3)
  - "IGOs and World Economic Policy in the perspective of Dependency Relationship," 1974 (Box 3)
  - Department of State: Proposal Evaluation of the UN System's Development Assistance Activities 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Environmental Protection Activities of International Organizations," 1979 (Box 3)
  - "The U.S. and World Order," 1982 (Box 3)
  - "National Entanglements in International Government Organizations," 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Congressional Hearings Statement 1985 (Box 3)
  - "Development, Human Dignity, and Peace," 1986 (Box 3)
  - "The UN System in the 1980s Crisis and Opportunity," 1987 (Box 3)
  - "Domestic Politics and International Relations" (Box 3)
  - "Soviet Policies Toward Economic and Social Aspects of the UN" (Box 3)
- Human Dimensions of Global Environmental Change
  The Human Dimensions of Global Environmental Change series (0.1 linear feet, 1988-1992) consists of materials relating to Jacobson's work in this research on human behavior as a factor in environmental change. It is subdivided into files such as research, publications, and hearings.
  - Framework for Research 1990 (Box 3)
  - World Climate Research Project 1990 (Box 3)
  - Articles
    - Environment Magazine, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Science Magazine, 1988 (Box 3)
    - National Geographic Research and Exploration Magazine, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Hearing on Priorities in Global Climate Change Research for the Committee on Science, Space and Technology," Washington, D.C. 1991 (Box 3)
  - Evaluation of Agenda 21 1992 (Box 3)
- University Materials
  The University Materials series (0.3 linear feet, 1957-1997) contains materials related to Jacobson's position as a professor at the University of Michigan. The files are made up of lecture notes, correspondence, awards, newsletter clippings, and documents related to Jacobson's tenure at the university.
  - Committee Appointments 1957-1972 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1976-1980 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters and Clippings 1958-1969 (Box 3)
  - Leaves of Absence 1964-1988 (Box 3)
  - Professional Activities Questionnaires 1979-1996
    - Faculty Personnel Records 1950-1985 (includes negatives of Jacobson) (Box 3)
  - Course Materials 1974-1997
    - Political Science 463-663
      - "Historical Development of IGOs", 2 folders (Box 4)
      - "Collective Security" (Box 4)
      - "Peaceful Settlement of Disputes" (Box 4)
      - "Disarmament" (Box 4)
    - Syllabi (Box 4)
- Published Materials
  The Publications series (0.1 linear feet, 1957-2001) consists of two folders of publications by Harold Jacobson. The publications are arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous Materials 1957-2001, 2 folders (Box 4)